Zachary K. Smith

10391 Old Dayton Rd. New Lebanon OH 45345 | 740-405-4219 | ezke.smith@gmail.com | smthzch.github.io

Summary

I am a data scientist/machine learning engineer with experience in end to end model development and deployment. I primarily work in Python but have released and maintained projects developed in C#, C++, and Java. Problems solved include processing large amounts of data on cloud infrastrusture, deploying models on orchestration services, and optimizing data collection. I have experience working on a diverse set of data modeling problems including deep learning on remote sensing data, Bayesian models on air quality sensor data, and optimal sequential decision making.

Experience

Senior Machine Learning Engineer

Aclima | Remote | October 2023 - Present

Data Scientist

January 2023 - September 2023

- Develop and deploy gas leak localization models to aid utilities in region prioritization (numpyro)
- Develop spatio-temporal models for air quality prediction using GPyTorch
- Refactor vehicle route planning code into modular python package for ease of expansion/testing
- Define and implement proper cross-validation scheme for flagship spatio-temporal model to quantify model improvements

Data Scientist

NCX | Remote | April 2021 - November 2022

- Build deep learning models to predict forest carbon using remote sensing data (pytorch)
- Process large scale geospatial vector and raster datasets (python, stac, xarray, rasterio)
- Create Bayesian Optimal Experimental Design package to target field data collection used to direct and optimize \$2M in data collection: ABODER
- Write custom algorithms in C++ to speed up data processing 100x

Data Scientist / Research Engineer

Aptima Inc. | Fairborn, OH | November 2018 - April 2021

- Develop particle filter based interior localization algorithm for iOS app
- Develop POMDP algorithms for adaptive training systems and agent based simulations (C#)
- Create predictive and anomaly detection algorithms for automated alert systems
- Develop Bluetooth/MQTT/Arduino based cognitive load measurement device (Arduino)

Associate Computational Biologist

UES Inc. | WPAFB, OH | June 2017 - November 2018

- Analyze high dimensional datasets for biomarker discovery of human physiological state
- High throughput sequencing analysis
- Provide statistical consultation and data analysis throughout the course of studies

Hydrology Technician

Miami Conservancy District | Dayton, Ohio | October 2012 - June 2017

- Create desktop / web / mobile applications for the collection, formatting, and uploading of field data including the server and database processes. (C#, Android/Java)
- Lead project development of web/map based data access applications for the public. (C#, Javascript)
- http://apps.mcdwater.org/waterapps/wellnetwork

Education

M.S. Applied Statistics

Wright State University | Dayton, Ohio | December 2018

B.S. Earth Science, Minor Soil Science

California Polytechnic State University | San Luis Obispo, California | June 2012

Skills

- Programming: Python, R, C/C++, C#, SQL, bash
- ML Frameworks: Scikit-Learn, PyTorch, GPyTorch, Stan, NumPyro
- Infrastructure: Docker, GCP, AWS, Databricks